<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indexing>
 <paragraph index="9" node_type="writer">Colorado River Foundational Principles – V1.0</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="11" node_type="writer">The Colorado River system has to work.  It needs to be in balance and sustainable,  For the river to work the math has to work.  There may be difficult choices ahead to achieve that end.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="12" node_type="writer">The United States must retain the ability to feed itself. In a tumultuous world, if we lose that ability, and the rest of the world chooses not to, we starve.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="13" node_type="writer">Good farm land is precious.  The best, most productive farmland, which is at the nexus of an ideal Ag economy is sacred.  It must be protected and improved, not fallowed and lost.  Once good farm land is lost its hard to recover.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="14" node_type="writer">Good farmers and ranchers are sacred, especially young ones.  They must be encouraged, assisted and protected, not driven out of the life they love by a cruel, unappreciative world.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="15" node_type="writer">Cities must have adequate clean water for health and safety, drinking, cooking, bathing and fire suppression.  Cities need green space, parks, swimming pools and even golf courses to be livable,.  Conversely, finding the balance between enough outdoor water use and too much is the challenge.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="16" node_type="writer">Rural communities are sacred, Not everyone wants to live in a city. The devastation that has been wrought by fallowing needs to end. </paragraph>
 <paragraph index="17" node_type="writer">Valuable ecosystems are sacred. They must get enough water to thrive. Once they are lost they are hard to recover. Conversely, marginal or doomed ecosystems shouldn’t use NEPA to drag down the entire system.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="18" node_type="writer">Water speculation must be discouraged without compromising free markets.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="19" node_type="writer">Litigation is the last resort of the desperate. Article VI, the non litigious, cooperative path must come first.  The Upper Basin can no longer succumb to litigation threats. School yard bully rules apply. We may lose but we will fight.</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="20" node_type="writer">The Upper Basin must not be sacrificed because it can’t compete with the ideal conditions in the Lower Basin.  The price the Lower Basin paid to get the high dam that creates those ideal conditions was the Colorado River Compact and the obscure wall between the two basins in Article III(a):</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="21" node_type="writer">(a) There is hereby apportioned from the Colorado River System in perpetuity to the Upper Basin and to the Lower Basin, respectively, the exclusive beneficial consumptive use of 7,500,000 acre-feet of water…</paragraph>
 <paragraph index="22" node_type="writer">Before the high dam the Lower Colorado flooded in the spring and went dry in the Winter, the Winter agriculture which now makes the Lower Basin special wasn’t there.  The high dam provided the power and water that made its cities thrive. To reiterate, the compact and “The Wall” was the price.</paragraph>
</indexing>
